Hi! Brandon here. It is National Novel Writing
Month. This is a challenge that happens every
year where writers are challenged to write a
novel in one month, loosely defining a novel
as 50,000 words. That definition is kind of vague.
Most of my novels are quite a bit longer. But
50,000 words is a doable but difficult challenge
for one month of writing. The goal of this
challenge is to get yourself out of a rut,
to force yourself to turn off your internal editor,
and to just write. It's a really great exercise.
I did it numerous times before I became a published
writer. In fact, The Way of Kings, which my
new book in the series is coming out this month,
was originally written as part of a National
Novel Writing Month challenge. So I think this
is a very worthy challenge. Like all things
in writing, it might not work for you.
I'm not going to be doing this. I'm going to be doing this
for a long time. I'm going to be doing this for a long time.
You may try it and find out it just,
your personal writing psychology, just does not mesh really well
with this type of challenge. You might find that
the writing you write, trying to follow a challenge
like this, just is not as good as if you
didn't. In that case, feel free to abandon it. However,
for those of you who want to try this and
have never done it before, I'm going to give you five
hacks, five ways that you can kind of
start writing a novel, perhaps without very much preparation,
and kind of force yourself to try this challenge. So
first one is something that a lot of us authors
do, which is called borrowing your structure.
Now, it doesn't happen with every novel.
In fact, it doesn't happen with every writer. But a
lot of times, books that we write come from us
watching a movie, reading a story, hearing about
an event, and really liking that genre or that
type of story, and saying, man, could I write something like that?
Could I write something like that? Could I write something like that?
Then as a writer, we dig into that subgenre, say
the heist novel, and say, what are some of the
aspects of this type of story that make them
really interesting? Why do I like a heist novel?
What about it is great? You know what? I
really like that heists involve a crew of different
people who all have a different speciality
who come together and apply their specialized talents
to achieving this really difficult goal.
And suddenly you have a story that,
as a writer, has a structure to it. You realize,
hey, we have a scene where you outline the problem.
We have a scene with each of
the characters being recruited, whether it's Ocean's Eleven,
or whether it is Armageddon, or whether
it is Inception. They all share some hallmark
pieces of their structure. You are followed
by some extra training or gathering of equipment
where they plan on how they're going to do
this. And then you have an ending where you bring
together everyone's specialized talents
to overcome the problem.
And then you have a movie where you
have a story that you're going to write about.
One way to get yourself into writing and kind
of maybe have, so to speak, some training wheels on,
is to go watch that movie and say, all
right, can I boil this down to its fundamental structure?
Then rebuild that structure with a new set
of characters and a new problem to solve,
and a new character arc that is my own.
A lot of times this works really well if you
transpose the genre. If you, say, really love
the stories that are told in Regency romances
done by Jane Austen, and you say, what if I
took this same structure and I made it a Western
instead? These sorts of transpositions can also help
you add a little more flair, a little bit
more of your own style, but you still, like
I said, have those training wheels. It doesn't have
to be training wheels, though. A lot of professional
writers will do this same sort of thing when
coming up with a story. They'll look to the
success of the story, and they'll look to the
success of the story. They'll look to the success
of the story. They'll look to the success of the
story. They'll look to the success of the story.
They'll look to the success of the story. They'll look
to the success of the story. They'll look to
the success of the story. They'll look to the successful
stories told of this trope in
the past and borrow that structure.
Do be aware that you shouldn't be enslaved by
that structure. You should be able to adapt it
to your story. But it really can
help, particularly if you're trying to write
something in one month, to have
a structure, an outline already provided.
Number two cool way to start writing a book if
you've never tried it is to begin with a monologue.
Even if your story isn't going to be
first-person perspective, meaning it's not going to be told,
from one character's viewpoint, telling the story as
they experienced it. You can still really get
into a character by basically interviewing them, or
having them tell you about a really important
time in their life, and you write it out
as if they were sitting there and telling you about
their story. A good friend of mine, Dan
Wells, several of his books began with him saying,
all right, if this character were going to
explain their life to me in five pages,
what would it be? And he wrote those five
pages, and then that was the character kind of explaining
themselves to Dan. Really, it was Dan
figuring out interesting things about this character.
Now, this probably won't end up in your final book.
But one of the cool things is, is if you
design it the right way, this can become,
pieces of this can be the little blurbs,
we call them epigraphs, at the start
of chapters. Could be excerpts from the character's
journal or diary or something like that. Maybe
you'll just love this format and write what we
want to write. But if you're going to write a
book, you're going to want to write a book that's
called an epistolary novel, which is a novel
written entirely in journal forms or in people's
writing. It's kind of the found footage version of
novels. So give that a try. Just have the
character write as if you
were them explaining about their life.
Number three, one way to really dig into
a character is to ask yourself, what does my
character want? What do they need? How are those
two things different? And why can't they have either
one? And if you ask yourself these things, it can
help you to generate and construct a plot even on
the fly. You start writing your characters.
Just sit down, start writing their everyday life,
figure out what it is that they really want.
Ask yourself how that's different from what they need.
Just do it as you're exploring this
character's life in the first few chapters.
Then start to construct the obstacles that keep
them from having these things that they want.
This is just a really good way to
start making sure that your story is character-centered.
If your story is turning around this character's
needs and wants, then you will naturally be
including the character in a lot of the story
decisions. One way you can go wrong with a book
is by making the character not want or need
anything. And a lot of times what will happen
is that character becomes an external observer
of some really interesting story happening with some
other character. And as a writing professor, I see
this quite a bit from new writers, where they've
picked the wrong viewpoint. Someone really interesting is
going to be the one who's going to be the one
who's going to be the one who's going to be the
one who's doing something. And this character
that they thought would be their main character
is just observing and commenting on it. You want
to avoid that. You want the story to be personal
to your viewpoint character. You always want to
be picking the viewpoint character who is either
changing the most, having the most conflict in
their life, or who is actively working on getting
what they want the most. Those are good ways
to choose who the protagonist of your story might be.
Now, number four is
going to go hand in hand with this.
Let's say you're working on this, but you're like,
Brandon, I still don't have a structure for
my story. I know what my character can't have.
I know why they want it so badly. And
I know the difference between their wants and their need.
I know what they think they want
and what will actually make them happy,
but I don't have a structure for my
story. In this case, number four tip is,
choose your type of progress. I have an entire lecture
on this, but if I boil it down, stories are
built from three ideas. They're a promise,
progress toward that promise, and a payoff on
that promise. And the progress part is the
important part. That's what the bulk of your
story is. We get pulled through stories. Things
become page turners because we can watch progress
toward a goal. And books naturally have this just in
the shape of the book. You get to watch. You're
like, this book is 500 pages long. As I
read, I'm getting closer to that ending. But you want
to reinforce this with some sort of plot that
you are showing progress toward. You're going to want
to reinforce this with some sort of
plot that you are showing progress toward.
Now, in a lot of stories, this
might be, for instance, a travelogue. You say,
we are starting in the Shire, and we are going
to end at Mount Doom, where the ring was forged.
And we can watch on the map as the
characters get closer and closer and closer. We can see
their progress. We can see where they
get diverted and can't go the direction where
they thought they were going to go, because
it's difficult. You want always in your story
to be moving in a direction,
mostly forward, sometimes backward. And this
progress does not have to be travelogue.
In a mystery, usually the progress is clues.
It's an information progress, meaning you have a
mystery. You don't know who killed this person.
Your characters are going to get clues, information that
build upon one another. And some of them are
false clues. Some of them are steps backward.
Some of them lead you in the wrong direction.
But you can get a sense as a reader that
more clues are gathering, and the image of who did
this is becoming more and more and more clear.
So decide your type of progress, and make sure
that you are signposting that progress is being
made. Most of the time, when readers complain
about a story not moving quickly enough, not
having good pacing, or not being a page turner,
it's because the author is not signposting the
type of progress that the story is supposed to
be making. You can misalign this sometimes. You
can say you're writing a romance when really
you're writing an adventure story, and so
you signpost the romance, but the reader's feeling
like we aren't making any progress because
you gave a bigger signpost about the adventure,
and there's no progress. But you give a
bigger signpost about the adventure, and there's a bigger
reader thinks this is what the story's about. It is
possible to do both hand in hand, and a lot of
stories do this. But my tip to you is decide
what type of progress are you going to expect the
reader to feel moving through the story, and make sure
you split that up, divide it up, give us a
trail of breadcrumbs along the way, indicating
that we're making that progress. The last piece
of advice I would give you to try to write a
book in a month is to prime your mind. Before I write,
I really like to do something else for a
little while. And if you're going to be writing
consistently to try and hit this 50,000-word goal, you're
going to be writing 1,700 words a day on
average is what I believe it's going to be. It's
a lot of writing if you haven't done it before.
And a lot of times you'll run into situations where
you're like, I have no idea what to do next.
One way to do it is to write a book, and then
you can write a book. And I'm going to give you a
little bit of advice on how to do that. One way to
do it is to write a book, and then you can write a
book. And a lot of times you'll run into
situations where you're like, I have no idea what
to do next. One way to avoid this is to
prime your mind with what you're going to write before.
This works really well when you have some sort of
empty space in your life where you can't be writing
because you're doing something, but you can
be thinking. Maybe it's during your commute.
Maybe it's during your morning workout.
Maybe it's when you're doing the dishes
or mowing the lawn, something that keeps
your body active but leaves your mind free.
Instead of letting it drift off,
say, all right, when I write
my next section of my story, what am I going
to do? What's the exciting thing I can have happen?
What is a way I can write this scene
that is going to feel different and interesting and
fascinating? Why will this scene be a
reader's favorite scene in this given book?
And imagine it. Play it through. Put on
headphones, if you're like me, and play some music
that matches the tone of the scene that you're
going to write. And prime yourself so that when
you sit down to work on that scene, you
just get going, because you've thought through this three
or four times during the commute, you know where
this story is going for this next 1500 words,
and you can just write it. This is really
handy if finding writing time in your life is difficult.
If perhaps you're not doing the November challenge,
but you still want to write a book,
and your life is just really hectic
during the week but you have time
during your commute, think during that commute, what am
I going to write? And then on the weekend
give yourself two hours and sit down and
get that stuff you imagined down on the page.
You will be surprised at how quickly you write.
But if you're not doing that, I encourage you to
write a book. I'll be happy to read it for you.
I'll be sure that you do. But I'm not going to write
a book. I'll be sure that you do. So don't bother
writing a book, you'll probably be surprised at how quickly you'll write.
at how quickly you write a novel if you
were able to dedicate some brain space to it.
Anyway, I hope that you'll
be successful in your writing journey.
I'll be back on this channel several times
during this month to give you some other
pieces of advice or maybe some pep talks on
how to write your novel. And good luck to you.